A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Walt Whitman 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
3829, etc., 5604
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
All deposits were made gifts on July 1, 1991.
3829: Deposit, November 20, 1951.
3829-a: Gift, December 1954.
3829-b: Gift, October 10, 1957.
3829-c: Void, books.
3829-d: Gift, February 11, 1958.
3829-e: Gift, November 30, 1959.
3829-f: Deposit, April 23, 1960.
3829-g: Deposit, April 30, 1960.
3829-h: Deposit, April 20, 1961.
3829-i: Deposit, April 24, 1961.
3829-j: Deposit, June 27, 1961.
3829-k: Purchase, November 29, 1962.
3829-l: Purchase, October 13, 1962.
3829-m: Purchase, October 2, 1962.
3829-n: Purchase, February 4, 1965.
3829-o: Archival transfer, July 23, 1965.
3829-p: Deposit, June 16, 1966.
3829-q: Deposit, March 9, 1967.
3829-r: Purchase, April 21, 1971.
3829-s: Deposit, September 29, 1971.
3829-t: Deposit, December 17, 1963.
3829-u: Deposit for copying, November 30, 1973.
3829-v: Gift, August 24, 1984.
3829-w: Purchase, November 5, 1985.
3829-x: Gift, November 7, 1986.
3829-y: Purchase, May 2, 1988.
3829-z: Transfer, July 12, 1989.
3829-aa: Purchase, July 15, 1996
3829-ab: Purchase, November 28, 2005
5604: Gift, May 1957.
7267: Gift, August 14, 1963
9778: Gift January 26, 1972
10204-az: Gift, December 28, 1998.
10602: Gift, June 18, 1984.
Biographical/Historical Information
For detailed biographical information, see the biography and chronology pages at the Whitman Archive.
Scope and Content
Literary Manuscripts (Series I) includes numerous drafts, editions, and revisions of many of Whitman's poems and articles. Included are manuscripts of Leaves of Grass, Song of Myself, Sea-Drift, As I Sit in Twilight, A Carol for Harvest for 1867, and biographical writings on Emerson, Carlyle, and Elias Hicks.
Miscellaneous Manuscripts (Series II), consists of legal documents, multiple versions of Walt Whitman's last will and testament, autograph signatures and envelopes, his Civil War diary written while visiting hospitals of the wounded in 1863, and a flower and pin he attached to his coat.
Correspondence (Series III), consists chiefly of Walt Whitman's personal correspondence; correspondents include Ellen C. Ahern, H. M. Alden, Jack Biriss, Richard Maurice Bucke, John Burroughs, Edward Carpenter, Edward Clifford, Peter Doyle, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Charles E. Feinberg, Charley Eldridge, Horace Howard Furness, Ann Gilchrist, J. B. Gilder, J. L. Gilder, Joseph Jackson, J. Johnston, Thomas Hancock Nunn, Jacob Klein, Edwin Miller, Albert B. Otis, James Parton, Abby H. Price, Ernest Rhys, T. W. Rollerston, J. H. Rome, Charles Rowley Jr., Oscar Wilde, and D. W. Zimmerman.
Miscellaneous Documents (Series IV), includes an advertisement for his lecture on Abraham Lincoln, publications, a mounted leaf from his tomb, the "Official Walt Whitman stamp and envelope" released in 1940, and a broadside for one of his poems: "Poem describing a Perfect School."
Photographs, Engravings, and Prints (Series V), consists of numerous photographs of Walt Whitman taken throughout his life, ranging from 1854 to 1892. There are also photographs of Mary Davis, Horace L. Traubel, Louisa Van Velsor Whitman (Whitman's mother), Walter Whitman (Whitman's father), Walt Whitman's dog, and various photographs of his house, the Walt Whitman statue, and the beaches he frequented.
Odds and Ends (Series VI), consists of the wrappers in which Leaves of Grass was housed when acquired by Clifton Waller Barrett and an unbound copy of Whitman's Manuscripts: Leaves of Grass (1860): a parallel text by Fredson Bowers.
Arrangement
The Papers of Walt Whitman are arranged in six series: Series I: Literary Manuscripts (arranged alphabetically by title); Series II: Miscellaneous Manuscripts (arranged chronologically); Series III: Correspondence (arranged chronologically by author); Series IV: Miscellaneous Documents (arranged chronologically); Series V: Engravings, Prints, and Photographs (arranged chronologically); and Series VI: Odds and Ends.
Contents List
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "The Absolute" 1872 June, AMs, 1 p. on 1 l. #3829-w. (Box-folder 1:1)
    Notes for a lecture on Homer and Emerson possibly given at Amherst College.
  - "After the Supper and Talk" [ca. 1885], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 25 cm. x 20 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:2)
    A draft of After the Supper and Talk on one composite leaf comprising at least seven irregularly cut fragments of different types of white paper pasted to each other and, collectively, to one leaf (25 x 20 cm.) of blue-ruled white laid paper with a partly visible watermark. In brown-black and black ink with extensive revisions in the same inks, in pencil, and in lighter brown ink. This poem was rejected by Harper's in 1885 but published in Lippincott's Magazine in November 1887, after which it eventually became the final poem in the "first annex" titled Sands at Seventy. To the verso are pasted sections 16 and 18-19 of Poem of Joys (final title: A Song of Joys ) clipped either from the independent book Passage to India (1871) or from the Passage to India supplement to Leaves of Grass. The section numbers of these lines are deleted in orange crayon, and the whole paste-on is deleted in pencil, with the pencil note, in a hand other than Whitman's, "Original mss/ Walt Whitman/ Poet" appearing to the right of it.
    This is an earlier draft than manuscripts located in the Feinberg Collection at the Library of Congress. The order of inscription seems to have been as follows, as deduced from incision patterns, paper types, and the overlap of letters on transferred sections of paper. First Whitman inscribed and heavily revised a draft of the poem on a section of gray-ruled wove paper. Wanting to avoid rewriting the clearest lines, he excised these (comprising the first two verses and the words "Shunning the..." from the original third verse) and pasted them to a section of blue-ruled wove paper with letterhead reading, in part, "Attorney.../ Washington...," apparently discarding the section of gray-ruled paper upon which the rest of the original verses appeared. These excised verses he drafted again on the blue-ruled paper. He then used a paste-on fragment of laid paper to revise the second half of the verse beginning "Shunning..."; at the end of the sentence, however, he deleted the period and added the words "so hard to unclasp his hand[s?]!" (That he added this as an afterthought is indicated by the fact that the half-line is crowded in over a preexisting curve along the lower edge of the laid fragment). Unsatisfied with the addition, he deleted part of it, tested and deleted the phrase "release those hands", deleted "so hard to," and then, out of space, squeezed a revision of this line in on the gray-ruled paper after the verse "Good-bye...repeating." It next occurred to Whitman to add an explanatory line beginning "(No more will they meet...)" after "hands," but since he had no space in which to do so he cut apart the composite leaf and pasted the two halves to a small section of wove paper—just large enough to hold the pieces together and afford room for the parenthesis. In revising the parenthesis, however, he ran out of space again. It was at this point that he obtained the large section of blue-ruled laid paper upon which the other sections are all overlaid, and, cutting away the second half of the parenthetical verse, pasted both of what were now composite half-leaves to the blue-ruled leaf. He then inscribed on this leaf the title, his revision of the rest of the parenthetical verse (in space he left between the composite halves), and the revised final verse. (It is difficult to determine at what point Whitman excised the title and last verse from the composite leaves, beyond noting that he did so before pasting the leaves to the blue-ruled section).
  - "And that was war..." n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., mounted. #3829-ac. (Box-folder 1:2-a)
  - "Another Day at Central Park" [1879], AMs, 5 pp. on 5 l., with typed transcript and engraving of Walt Whitman. #3829-k. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - "As I Sit in Twilight, Late..." [ca. 1865 or 1888], AMsS, 6 pp. on 5 l. Brown bound volume measuring 34.5 cm. x 27.5 cm. #3829-k. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Pasted to leaves in the volume are five variations on the poem As I Sit in Twilight, Late. A transcription of the final version begins the volume.
    - Page 1: As I Sit in Twilight, Late, or twilight song, ca. 1865 or 1888, 1 leaf, handwritten, 30 cm. x 22 cm. Written in pencil.
    - Page 2: As I sit in twilight alone by the flicker, ca. 1865 or 1888, 1 leaf, handwritten, 26 cm. x 20 cm. Written in pencil.
    - Page 3: As I sit in twilight, ca. 1865 or 1888, 1 leaf, handwritten, 27 cm. x 20 cm. Written in pencil.
    - Page 4: Unknown (As I sit in the twilight), ca. 1865 or 1888, 1 leaf, handwritten, 28.5 cm. x 19.5 cm. Written in pencil.
    - Page 5: Unknown (A million hidden names), ca. 1865 or 1888, 1 leaf, 27.5 cm. x 21 cm. Written in pencil.
  - "As of Forms" n.d., AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., 21.5 x 13 cm., with transcription, Barrow. #3829 (Bowers #1). (Box-folder 1:5)
  - "Asthetics-Arts-Science" after 1857, AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 21 cm. x 12 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:6)
    This manuscript contains notes about the intellects of Plato and Aristotle. According to Floyd Stovall in The Foreground to Leaves of Grass (Charlottesville, U of Virginia P, 1974, p. 176), these notes are based on F.W. Schlegel's Lectures on the History of Literature (NY, 1841, 99f. or London [Bohn ed.], 1859, 82ff).
  - "Audobon [sic] proposed...", on same leaf as "Paul Jones."
  - "A Backward Glance O'er Traveled Roads" [ca. 1888], AMs fragment, 1 p. on 1 l., Barrow. Written in ink with color pencil revisions. With transcription. #3829-a. (Box-folder 1:8)
    Noted as the preface to November Boughs of 1888.
  - "the best parts of literature and religion..." [1874], AMs fragment, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 14 cm. x 19.5 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:9)
    A partial draft of prose considering the nature of God and religion written on the verso of letter from Johnston dated 1874. The relationship of this prose to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - "The Bible as Poetry" [ca. 1883], AMs fragment, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 21 cm. x 13.5 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:10)
    This manuscript is a draft of part of Whitman's essay The Bible as Poetry, which was published first in The Critic on February 3, 1883. On the verso is letter dated January 13, 1883 from D.M. Zimmerman of the Camden and Atlantic Railroad, which offers Whitman a complimentary rail pass.
  - "Biographical Note of Walt Whitman" [ca. 1888], AMs, 3 pp. on 3 l. #3829 (Bowers #29). (Box-folder 1:11)
  - "British human beings-Wild Men-the 'koboo'" [late 1850's], AMs, 1 p. on 1 l., handwritten, 22 cm. x 12 cm. #3829-i. (Box-folder 1:12)
    This manuscript contains notes about certain aboriginal peoples. A short article entitled The Wild Men of Borneo is pasted toward the bottom of the leaf. The relationship of this manuscript to Whitman's published work is unknown.
  - "Broadway" [ca. 1888, March 3], AMsS, 1 p. on 1 l., 22.5 cm. x 20 cm. #3829-a. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Note at top of page states "Sent Herald March 3—sent again April 9 '88." Written in purple pencil.
  - "A Carol for Harvest for 1867" n.d., AMs, 29 leaves. #3829 (Bowers #2). (Box-folder 1:14)
    Including "The Return of the Heroes." On 29 pages, many of them composite leaves, comprising five different cuttings or packs of paper on which two or more leaves are inscribed, and other cuttings on which only one leaf is inscribed. All but a handful of the leaves are inscribed on white laid paper ruled in light blue-green on both sides or on all of one side and some of the other. In his 1954 edition and study of the manuscript in Modern Philology (vol. 52, no. 1), Fredson Bowers grouped the leaves by cutting-type as follows (letters having been added here for convenience). Type A: Leaves 1 and 21. Type B: Leaves 2-3. Type C: Leaves 4-5 and 15-16. Type D: Leaves 6-9, 12-14, and 19. Type E: Leaves 17-18. As Bradley and Blodgett note, this poem was first published in the September, 1867 issue of The Galaxy and reprinted in the London-based Tinsley's Magazine in October of that year. After appearing with various revisions in the 1871 Passage to India and the 1876 Passage to India supplement to Two Rivulets, the poem was permanently retitled The Return of the Heroes. This took place in the 1881 edition of Leaves, where the poem appeared without its original first two verse paragraphs. At one point this manuscript was in the possession of Whitman scholar Clara Barrus, who clipped to Whitman's title page a note including these lines: "...Precious souvenirs, given me by Thos. B. Harned, one of Whitman's literary executors. You can almost feel Walt's heart beat in these lines." This and other short notes by Barrus have been unclipped from the leaves. Annotations by Barrus (or another collector with a similar hand) are mentioned when significant enough to warrant attention, but are otherwise left undescribed.
    - Page 1: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5
      On a section of type A paper measuring 19.5 x 12.5 cm. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed in pencil on both sides, with no revisions on the recto (title page) but some on the verso, where the lines (beginning "As a huge muse[eum?] mowing") are deleted with a single vertical pencil stroke. The title is underscored three times. The lines on the verso were revised to constitute verse paragraph 29 in section 12 of the 1871 published version of the poem; in 1881 the verse paragraphs were not numbered and this section was permanently renumbered 8.
    - Page 2: 1 leaf, handwritten, 10.5 x 12.5 cm. pasted to 6.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a composite leaf, type B, formed by joining the upper section of verses excised from what is now the lower section of Leaf 3 to the head of another set of verses by means of a section of the same paper pasted to the verso. The upper section measures 10.5 x 12.5 cm., the lower section measures 6.5 x 12.5 cm., and the backing strip measures 8 x 12 cm. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed in black ink, with heavy revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Whitman's boxed pencil note "Harvest carol for 1867" runs up the left margin, followed by the unboxed note "1867—the great/ Harvest." (The second line at the top of the leaf, deleted, reads "The great Harvest of 1867"). After further revision these sections became, respectively, verse paragraphs 1 and 2 (together comprising section 1) of the 1871 version of the poem. In 1881, this entire section, as noted above, was deleted from the poem.
    - Page 3: 1 leaf, handwritten, 11 x 12.5 cm. pasted to 9.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a composite leaf, type B, formed by joining the section of verses beginning "For the Lands..." to the lower set of verses excised from what is now the upper section of Leaf 2. The sections measure as follows: 11 x 12.5 cm. (upper); 9.5 x 12.5 cm. (lower); 8 x 12 cm. (backing). Inscribed in black ink, with revisions in the the same ink and in pencil. Barrus jotted down the 1881 title and page number at the top of the leaf, along with the note "I—." With further revision—including the deletion of the last line, beginning "O theatre of Time,..."—these sections became verse paragraphs 3 and 4 (comprising section 2) of the 1871 version of the poem. In 1881 these paragraphs went unnumbered and, with the deletion of the original first section, together formed section 1 of the poem (hence the "I" added by Barrus).
    - Page 4: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type C paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), inscribed in black ink, with several revisions in the same ink. Whitman penned in the note "?unfailing" in the upper right corner of the leaf. Someone else, it seems—most likely Barrus—added the pencil note "—2—" in the top center of the page. Multiple pinholes in center. With a few small revisions these verses together with those on Leaf 5 became verse paragraph 5 (section 3) of the 1871 published version of the poem. In 1881 section 3 became section 2.
    - Page 5: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type C paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), inscribed in black ink, with heavy revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Multiple pinholes in center. The first few deleted lines on the page constitute false starts. After further revision the remaining lines joined revised lines from Leaf 4 in section 3 (verse paragraph 5) of the 1871 version of the poem, and stayed with the Leaf 4 lines in section 2 of the 1881 version.
    - Page 6: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.). Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised in pencil, with a single revision in brown-black ink. Barrus or another annotator, it seems, added the number "—3—" in the top center of this leaf. With some small revisions these lines became verses 1-6 of verse paragraph 6 (section 4) of the 1871 version, and in 1881 they comprised verses 1-6 of section 3. Leaves 7-9 contain the verses that would eventually complete this section, and, as Bowers notes, leaves 6-9 come from the same pack of paper, are all inscribed and revised in the same media, and feature matching pinhole patterns.
    - Page 7: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12 cm.). Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and extensively revised in pencil. Two deleted false starts appear at the head of the leaf. With some slight further revisions these lines became verses 7-9 of section 4 (verse paragraph 6) in the 1871 version of the poem; in 1881 they comprised verses 7-9 of section 3.
    - Page 8: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised in pencil, with one correction in brown-black ink. With slight revisions these lines became verses 10-12 of section 4 (verse paragraph 6) in the 1871 version of the poem; in 1881 they constituted the same part of section 3.
    - Page 9: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper measuring 19.5 x 12.5 cm., with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and heavily revised in pencil. All of the verses below the half-point of the page are deleted with a diagonal pencil stroke. The remaining line was incorporated in the 1871 version of the poem as the final verse (13) of section 4 (verse paragraph 6), a position it maintained in section 3 of the 1881 version.
    - Page 10: 1 leaf, handwritten, 10 x 12.5 cm. pasted to 13.5 x 12.5 cm. pasted to 6 x 12.5 cm.
      On a composite leaf formed by pasting together three sections (10 x 12.5, 13.5 x 12.5, and 6 x 12.5 cm.) of the white laid blue-ruled paper. Multiple pinholes in the area that becomes the center of the leaf when the bottom section is folded up. All three sections are inscribed in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Barrus or another annotator has added the number "—4—" in pencil at the head of the leaf. With some small revisions these lines became section 5 (verse paragraphs 7-10) of the 1871 version of the poem, and in 1881 they constituted the first three verse paragraphs of section 4.
    - Page 11: 1 leaf, handwritten, 20 x 13 cm.
      On a leaf of white laid paper (20 x 13 cm.) formerly creased in the middle and bearing a papermaker's seal (which appears to read "W.H."[?]) in the upper left corner. A very small fragment of newspaper or other printed matter (reading "All hea.../ Made") is affixed to the verso. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed very tightly in black ink, with extensive revisions in the same ink and in pencil. Whitman's pencil number 2 appears to the left of the verse beginning "Pass;—then rattle drums again..." This section was originally the beginning of an independent poem with the title Pass and room O proud brigades/ By Walt Whitman (deleted in pencil here), indicating, as Bowers and others have noted, that A Carol of Harvest, for 1867 began life as two poems, one celebrating the abundant harvest of that year and another dealing with the human costs of the Civil War. With some small revisions the contents of this page became section 6 (verse paragraphs 11-12) of the 1871 version of the poem, and in 1881 they comprised the second two unnumbered verse paragraphs of section 4.
    - Page 12: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed in (badly smudged) pencil, with extensive revisions in pencil and in brown-black ink. These lines were revised to constitute verse paragraphs 13 and 14 (section 7) of the 1871 version of the poem; in 1881 they comprised the first two unnumbered verse paragraphs of section 5.
    - Page 13: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and heavily revised in pencil, with several revisions in brown-black ink. These lines were revised to constitute verse paragraph 15 (section 7) of the 1871 version of the poem, and in 1881 made up the final unnumbered verse paragraph of section 5.
    - Page 14: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm., On a section of type D paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), with three pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised in pencil on both sides. The recto lines represent a relatively early draft of what would become verse paragraphs 16 and 17 (the first part) in section 8 of the 1871 version of the poem, which would go on to make up the first two unnumbered verse paragraphs of section 6 in the 1881 version. The verso lines (beginning "But I must bring/ the dead"), deleted with a single curved pencil stroke, constitute an earlier version of the lines on Leaf 12.
    - Page 15: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type C paper (19.5 x 12.5 cm.), with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The recto lines were revised to constitute the second part of verse paragraph 17 and all of verse paragraph 18 (section 8) in the 1871 version of the poem. In 1881 they made up most of the second and all of the third unnumbered verse paragraphs of section 6. The verso lines (beginning "Now a passage/ of/ Exultation"), deleted with a single vertical pencil stroke, seem more like a note from Whitman to himself than a draft of poetic verses, but the word "Exult" does appear on leaves 15 and 16, as in verse paragraph 20 (section 9) of the 1871 version.
    - Page 16: 1 leaf, handwritten, 20 x 12.5 cm.
      On a section of type C paper (20 x 12.5 cm.), with multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed in black ink and in pencil, with extensive revisions in pencil. The ink verse "Exult O lands! under/ the powerful sun!" (which was revised on Leaf 17), along with other trial verses in pencil, are all deleted with several pencil strokes. The remaining verses at the foot of the leaf were revised to form verse paragraph 19 (section 9) in the 1871 version of the poem, which became the fourth unnumbered verse paragraph in section 6 of the 1881 version.
    - Page 17: 1 leaf, handwritten, 19.5 x 11 cm.